我哋夠法定人數。
噉我哋而家開會啦，我哋請誒團體代表入嚟先，同埋官員啦，好啊。
早晨啊，咁多位。
誒本人僅代表咧，我哋法案委員會嚇，就係歡迎各位團體嘅代表同埋公眾人士咧出席今日嘅會議嘅。就二零一二年嘅税務及印花税法例另類債券計劃修訂條例草案咧，係發表意見嘅。我哋都歡迎政府當局嘅代表咧係。
出席今次嘅會議。
需要即時傳譯服務嘅議會人士咧。
請戴上你哋嘅耳筒，並且按需要咧選擇呢個頻道嚇。
座位上面咧已經顯示各語言嘅頻道㗎啦。
今日共有。
七個團體係出席我哋呢個會議發言嘅，另外亦都有九位誒團體嘅代表咧，佢誒亦都唔會出席呢個會議，但係佢提交咗書面嘅文件嘅。
我會先請各團體代表輪流發言，每一個團體嘅發言時間咧有五分鐘嘅。
團體發言完畢之後，我會請政府當局咧係作出初步嘅回應。委員隨後咧可以向團體代表或者政府咧係提問㗎。
根據慣常嘅做法，秘書處咧係已經將所有收到嘅意見書咧。
係上載喺立法會嘅網頁上面。倘若團體代表未有提交書面意見，或者係仲有補充嘅話咧，就請盡快喺會後向我哋提交，好嘛？
我亦都會提醒各位出席嘅團體代表，你哋嘅意見書同埋喺會上嘅發言。
均不會享有立法會嘅權利及特權條例所規定嘅保障同埋豁免嘅。
啊！噉我首先咧就會請黎亞明律師行嘅黎亞明先生發言嘅。
Thank you.
from from my perspective, I really have two points to make. One is that I'm glad to see the way that it's been drafted, which is basically the shell contains the primary elements, allowing a great deal of freedom.
嗯。
within the type of structure that can be formulated.
The other point I'd like to make is that I think in the DIPN and the SOIPN, there should be some references to the materials. Given that these are based on Islamic finance, there should be some materials allowing the commissioner and the collector to allow persons to refer to that. I'm not.
Saying that you should mention Sharia or Islamic within that, but at least that would give confidence to those who are outside Hong Kong to understand that these are based on Islamic principles, but without necessarily referring to Islamic principles. Because I agree it should be neutral in terms of the use of Islam or
Muslim, which is understandable, and given the differences within the Islamic world, I think it's probably better for Hong Kong if we leave it neutral, following England, and that would be easier for the way the
The instruments are structured.
我 also got some other points on the possibility of records being kept in electronic form, and also the possibility under the stamp duty ordinance of having some sort of tax certificates, but without the interest element in it, as a means by which to deal with the security issue.
That's left in the other part.
Apart from that, I have no further comments as far as I'm concerned from my company. Thank you.
咁咧就誒黎亞明先生咧，佢就係誒。
以一位獨立嘅會誒律師咧係發言嘅，噉啊佢亦都係律師會嘅代表。
噉我相信佢剛才已經係表達咗佢哋嘅意見，同埋佢嘅誒，佢哋嘅意見咧，亦都喺書面上面咧，都係好清楚㗎啦。
噉啊，高志豪先生咧，佢就出席咗我哋嘅會議，但係佢又唔準備咧係發言嘅。咁所以，我哋誒亦都都會係誒睇到佢嗰個書面嘅意見啦嚇。咁下一位咧係誒花旗銀行嘅。
啊，Mr. Osmond-Evans。
please。
Good morning, thank you very much for giving us the opportunity to be part of this effort. Just a quick introduction. I am the head of the Islamic Banking Business for Citigroup for Asia, and prior to that, I was also the CEO for the Global Islamic Business based out of Dubai. We welcome this initiative. We think it is.
very important as a financial centre, one of the global financial centres for Hong Kong to have the ability to offer Islamic finance to both public and private sector enterprises, and to level the playing field by virtue of this bill.
We do think that the flexibility that's offered through the various types of structures, as contemplated herein, will allow both the public and the private sector to tap the widest possible investor base, both from Asia as well as from the Middle East.
We have been extensively involved with the recommendations process to date, and at this point, we don't really have any specific concerns about any particular aspects of of the bill. We think that should this be be passed, it will encourage issuers from
Hong Kong to tap the Islamic finance market in in various formats, depending on the kind of assets that are available from their portfolio. There are of course certain structures that are more preferred in the Middle East than others. That has been highlighted, you know, in the.
past, but again this is a very fast growing field and there's a lot of innovation that has happened over the last few years.
We have been involved extensively with bringing in first-time issuers from Dubai, from Bahrain, from Malaysia, Indonesia, even the German state of Saxony-Anhalt to the Islamic finance market, and the structures that are contemplated here, whether.
The sale and lease base structure, or the purchase and sale base structure, or the investment base structure, they have all been used, including the agency based structure as well, in various forms in precedent sukuk transactions. So we very confident that these will continue to.
remain， you know， acceptable in the Islamic investor universe， and the specific application of these in the Hong Kong market should not cause any concerns for investors who are looking to also diversify from their home market and。
alternative， you know， avenues for investment of the Islamic capital。
Thank you very much.
Thank you。噉我哋都歡迎啊，花旗銀行咧另外一位同事咧係出席出席咗呢個會議嘅，就係Mr. Oliver Go。就誒一陣間，如果有機會嘅話咧，佢誒如果有同事發問嘅話，佢都可以回應嚇。
噉啊，下一位咧就係財資市場工會嘅張耀炯先生，張生。
Thank you very much for inviting me to be here today. The Treasury Markets Association has been following with interest the government's initiatives to develop Islamic finance in Hong Kong over the past few years.
我們 pleased to see the introduction of this bill into the Legislative Council.
which is a positive and important step forward towards furthering the development of Islamic finance, and in particular a sukuk market in Hong Kong.
The Islamic financial industry has become an increasingly important part of the global financial markets, and by developing Islamic finance, Hong Kong can further diversify its financial platform and enhance its standing as an international financial centre and an asset management hub.
提供一些背景，TMA的工作組就發展伊斯蘭 finance 在香港，曾進行過一項研究，幾年前，發現結構，通常涉及使用特殊目的車輛和多次資產轉移，可能吸引額外。
tax liabilities and stamp duty charges.
when compared with conventional bonds.
Thus, suitable changes or clarifications would be needed to the tax laws in Hong Kong.
in order to provide a level playing field.
for the issuance of sukuk， compared with conventional bonds.
We note that the intention of the bill is precisely so, and we believe that the proposed amendments will help to align the tax and stamp duty treatment for common types of sukuk with their conventional counterparts.
thereby providing a level playing field between the two.
我們支持被提出、規範性及宗教中立的approach，採 adopted by the bill。
which has also been adopted in the United Kingdom and some other jurisdictions.
我們也樂見，經過去年由FSTB進行的諮詢後。
coverage of the bill has now been expanded to accommodate the agency arrangement.
this structure is becoming increasingly popular in the sukuk market, and several landmark sukuk transactions from the Middle East and Malaysia have been structured using this agency structured in recent years.
從一個市場 perspective，我們希望這個法案會被通過迅速，所以市場參與者可以盡快利用香港的金融平台發行期貨。
passage of the bill will remove a big impediment for issuers considering to issue sukuk, and will also open up more options and opportunities for market players.
Thank you very much.
下位係香港中銀。
資產管理有限公司行政總裁阿歐景麟先生，歐生，係啊，主席啊，各位議員同埋各位朋友啊，我哋啊好支持呢個草案嘅。噉我係啊想講一講咧，我哋係用一個啊market practitioner個角度去睇呢個草案啊，因為其實我哋覺得個時間咧係相當之好嘅，因為其實大。
大家都見到呢個人民幣國際化咧，係行得越嚟越快嘅。咁喺我哋嗰個submission嗰度咧，我哋講咗有兩個原因啦。其實一個就係咧，啊，如果喺一個啊大衞嘅環境睇咧，啊，美國喺能源嗰方邊咧，啊，喺好多方邊咧，亦都有嘅估計。其中一個係啊BP啦，喺舊年咧出咗一個。
個report咧都幾震撼嘅。佢就係估計咧，啊美國喺二零三零年嘅時候咧，已經可以咧係完全自己喺啊呢個資啊能源嗰邊獨立㗎啦。咁如果你睇翻呢個發展咧，嗯喺中東嗰方邊咧，佢一定要揾一個另外一個啊啊buyer啦，個customer。噉你可以睇到咧，中國係而家已經喺啊能源同。
同埋喺依個誒。
commodities嗰方面咧有一個最大嘅consumer啦，咁所以我哋覺得咧啊中國啊同埋中東嗰個關係咧只會越嚟越密切。咁喺McKinsey咧亦都有個啊projection咧喺拜二零二零年咧嗰個trade flow咧係講緊大約三百五十至五百個billion嘅。其實我哋覺得依個可能係一個underestimate添啊under。
估測。
嗯，咁點解啊？我哋覺得啊，依一個啊標係啊對香港好重要咧，就係因為大家都知道，其實香港已經係一個人民幣嘅啊交易中心。噉我哋都好啊積極咧去發展依個點心債依個市場。咁但係如果當中國同中東嗰個啊啊交易咧個量越嚟越大嘅。
時候咧，咁亦都咧啊！相信咧，好大部分呢一個將來嘅交易咧，都係用人民幣交收嘅。咁如果人民幣交收嘅就係，即係交之話咧，就係誒中東嘅投資者咧手上嘅人民幣會越嚟越多。噉佢哋都要需要投資嘅產品。咁所以，我覺得如果呢個草案過咗之後咧，香港咧喺呢方面咧發展嘅潛力係會好大。咁亦都相。
相信咧，亦都啊，好多中資嘅公司亦都想喺中東去發展。噉，如果依個啊，如果有依個啊，
啊，super呢啲噉嘅產品出現咧，咁亦都會幫助到咧啊！依個啊capital market嘅啊發展噉，所以我覺得啊，香港啊，如果pass過境過咗呢個草案草案之後咧，噉我覺得香港嗰個喺啊人民幣嗰個國際中心發展咧，唔單止淨係好似而家噉嘅規範，可能亦都會。
發展到咧去誒二三億翻零師方面。
係，好啊！多謝你，歐生。
誒，我哋下一位係九龍清真寺香港總教長嘅。
誒，艾爾沙特先生，Mr. Ash。
Thank you very much. Good morning.
I'm grateful for inviting me on this important meeting.
And I would like to tell about the basic difference between conventional banking on bonds and sukuk.
Islamic religion has introduced a economic system to the world, and that has been practiced for last two decades. And more than 200 financial institute are expering exper are doing experience on Islam.
Finance.
和伊斯蘭， has forbidden to deal with the usury or interest. This is the basic law of the religion of Islam.
和第二個重要 aspect，就係應該沒有誤會。誤會就係。
There should be no speculation.
在金融系統， no artificial money is allowed in the religion of Islam and
在伊斯蘭教信仰，的 dealing。
Trading in in the debts are not allowed. Though Islamic sukuk is is a product that is based on actual product actual things, not only dealing with the debts. So this is the basics.
在Islamic finance and Sukuk is one of the product, not the complete Islamic finance. And if we see in the Hong Kong, it is a great market for the Muslim as for as for the non-Muslim. For the Muslims, they are
係，bound to deal as per the instruction or the guidance of the faith or the religion of Islam. So, is according to Islam, the a Muslim cannot deal with usury or interest. So, for them, there is a limitation in especially in Hong Kong. But if
你 adopt the Islamic finance, indeed there will be an opportunity for the Muslims as well as for others to to make the business to make the deal. So the the first and the most important thing that I appreciate for the government who who is introducing the Islamic
Finance in Hong Kong. Indeed, I hope, as you have seen in the past few years, the worldwide
There will be turmoil in the economic system in economic in banking. It was because of artificial money. It was because of trading in the debts. So Islamic finance were saved in the past. So it should be adopted. And the most important thing here in Hong Kong that we need that.
是的，mortgage、Islamic mortgage、Islamic finance，因為有好多product in Islamic finance。一係the sukuk，一係the takaful，即係等於保險。一係the basalam，一係the istisna。
one is this mortgage. the mortgage again, it is the protection of the bank as well as the protection of individual. so it should be adopted. so Islamic finance
believes in profit and loss sharing, not only sharing in the profit.
所以伊斯蘭也給出，了利益給兩方，所以應該以一種方式來採納，這樣對所有人都有利。另一個重要的點是伊斯蘭伊斯蘭金融賣出商品時，
comes into the position.
If someone has no position, then he cannot trade. So it is again a protection for the parties. And purchasing and selling of loan is also prohibited. Islamic finance says that no gain without either.
efforts or liability.
所以如果它被採納，我認為許多穆斯林會獲益，同時其他人士也會有機會透過這個項目賺錢。我非常感謝香港政府提出這個法案。
Okay, thank you.
下一位係自前培訓及教育機構嘅何麗儀女士。
Good morning. We have submit our view and we have no further addition. However, I would like to highlight that Hong Kong is in need of well trained finance professionals to work on this alternative bond and the subsequent Islamic finance products, if there is any in the future.
manpower development in this respect should be part of the plan in the introduction of this initiative.
The administration should give recognition to suitable qualification, both training and practical. Thank you very much. Thank you.
好，政府有冇咩回應啊？
誒多謝主席。誒誒，如果主席容許我，或者誒用英文作出一啲簡單嘅誒總體嘅回應，或者一陣嘅討論，我哋睇下嘅情況。啊，So，like the chairman，I would like to take this opportunity to thank for the speakers who spoke just now and those organisations.
和 persons who have submitted written submissions to the Bills Committee, expressing their views on legislative proposal for the introduction or to remove existing hurdles for the development of Islamic finance in Hong Kong. At this stage, the development of sukuk.
In Hong Kong, so from our point of view, I must express our appreciation for the overwhelming support we heard just now for this legislative initiative. I think that sort of overwhelming support, based on
三個原因，第一，There is actually a need on the ground for the development of Islamic finance， especially in Hong Kong as an international financial centre。
That market development present us with a very good opportunity in terms of timing. We have just heard about from the market practitioners how they see the the development of this market now vis-a-vis the development of Hong Kong, especially the development of Hong Kong as an offshore.
Shore RMB Centre， we think that this is a very good marriage of various factors leading to the Hong Kong's unique position and advantage in developing this market.
The second point is we do recognise there are hurdles on the way, and the biggest hurdle now is in the taxation taxation regime that we have, that may put Islamic bonds or sukuk, because of their unique characteristics, that has been just very well explained just now from.
What we heard that that may require some changes in our legislation so that they would develop on the same footing as other conventional bonds from the taxation perspective. So along the way, in order to achieve that objective, we do have to think of the best way.
The best approach in terms of drafting the legislation, and I'm glad to hear that there was support expressed just now for the proposed legislative framework we have put in the bill, mainly by putting the various structure and nature in the principal legislation.
and setting out the conditions, but some of those conditions will be further explained in the DIPN to be issued by the taxation authorities. So we took note of some comments on the need for some reference to the characteristics of these products or the bigger bigger.
Context in the in the DIPN, we will duly consider these suggestions while the taxation draw authorities draw up their practical guidance note on this respect. The third reason for I think the support we heard, of course, I would of course hesitate.
to mention that on on the individual comments on the drafting of the bill on the very specific wording, I think we can also take the opportunity of the bill's committee's scrutiny process, ensuring process to look in into them in further detail.
But I would just say that the third and last, but not the least, reason for the support perhaps is that we have admittedly taken some time in drawing up the proposed legislation, since the first idea or the concept was mooted with the market, because.
There are quite a lot of complexities and technical considerations involved, and also we have taken time to consult the market with professional organisations or with individual market practitioners during the process before we actually put pen to paper in drawing.
Up the bill, so we we of course put out public consultation earlier on, and we received very useful comments.
and in in the in the form of the bill we we we saw we we see or have been presented to the bills committee, actually they have reflected quite number of comments received from the market or commentators during the consultation process, mainly.
on the coverage that some speakers have just mentioned, we expand the scope of the coverage of the Sukuk products.
And talking about, I think one speaker just now commented the bill allow feasibility. That that is true. Because even in terms of coverage, we we build in some feasibility in the bill so that if market development requires so, we
With the FS financial secretary's authorisation and with the legislative approval, we can introduce further products type under the bill. So similar flexibilities are built into the bill, and other other
Comments we have taken into account regards those for example other record keeping period limitation period etc so I think I would just leave the time open for for further discussions and we look forward.
作為講者所講，一個比較 speedy 篩查的法案，與法案委員會，所以我們可以有這個工具和基礎設施，給伊斯蘭教會和更廣泛的社區，以及在這個領域工作的專業人士，這樣他們可以真正開始。
more initiatives in this respect. Thank you, Chairman. Okay, thank you.
唔該曬，秘書長。
啊，呢位警員。
係多謝主席，亦都歡迎誒今日嚟參與我哋會議，畀意見我哋嘅團體誒。普遍頭先政府嘅回應都係團體裏邊發言嘅內容，大家都係對於誒呢一個草案咧係表示歡迎，亦都誒相信咧會有助推動香港伊斯蘭金融嘅發展。噉我都誒諗。
留意到咧，有部分今日冇嚟誒參加表述意見嘅團體，都有啲書面嘅意見。主席咁咧，其中誒有啲會計師行啦，同埋誒。
誒。
同埋law society咧都表示有啲問題，噉我都想請教下今日嚟誒表達意見嘅團體同埋政府對於呢啲嘅誒。
內容嘅回應，咁其中一個咧就係大家都不約而同噉樣去對於草案裏邊有一個要求就係叫reasonable commercial return condition，就認為係好難界定嘅，亦都有意見認為咧就要將佢刪除嘅。咁究竟呢個你哋嘅理解是否係一致咧？同埋有冇啲咩？
意見可以畀到我哋同埋政府咧。另外就係嗰個關於嗰個maximum term length condition of fifteen year，咁亦都有意見認為咧，就係誒未必係誒需要有呢一個maximum term length condition嘅。噉我想聽下團體嘅意見，有冇團體願意回答咧？嚇，唔該。
好。
誒有冇邊位想誒表達下意見？
阿黎亞明先生咧，就喺佢嗰個意見書裏邊有提到呢個問題嘅。The law side is actually already made its comments on that, and they've suggested in relation to reasonable return. I think that's something that needs some consideration, also to the
the period which the
Some sort of deposit to be kept. I think that is also something that needs consideration because of the long term effect of that. No solutions have been suggested, but I think the law society's views on paragraph four clearly after having a meeting with the law society that was the concern.
of some of the members, and I think that needs to be addressed in the bill or perhaps the the relevant DIPN or SOIPN to make it clear. Otherwise, it would make it
difficult for those people wishing to introduce products, and it could actually be a disincentive. So I think that's a crucial element that needs to be considered. The law side has also looked at some other elements, so I'm not repeating, which is about definition about material time because the arguments are the circuitus. But in relation to the
Just media's law side has considered that, and it's of the view that the administration should look at that carefully.
thank you.
歐生會唔會有啲咩意見？
即喺呢個term嗰方面咧，即係你你哋做做呢個資產管理嘅，噉啊將來如果真係要發行呢一個噉樣嘅伊斯蘭債券嘅時候，你你覺得有冇咩問題？
啊啊，主席啊，我得啊，如果個年期可以啊隨便嘅，梗係最好啊。噉啊，另外一個嗰個頭先嘅嗰個reasonable return嘅definition啊，我都同意。如果嗰個可以清晰啲嘅咧啊，咁變咗市場啊運作嘅時候會知道嗰個框框喺邊度。
好啊。
其他朋友有冇咩意見啊？接收呢筆高，一個補充嗰個reasonable誒return咧誒。
即係因為頭先提到咧，因為shuku嚟講咧，佢安排咧係要需要個feasibilities嘅。咁往往咧，佢嗰個financial arrangement因為咧，佢唔可以計個利息個interest啊。
咁變咗咧，可能咧係喺個arrangement裏面咧，可能at a discount。
或者咧係一啲inform of一啲additional charges，或者個banking charges。
嚇咁可能你喺個taxation裡面啦嚇，即係個substance over form。咁因為如果你一用substance over form，你你好難做落去。咁變咗咧，我諗呢度可以大家考慮下咧，就誒用一個reasonable誒terms嚇嚟嚟包括咗佢，反而咧可以係後面。
面咧喺實施嘅過程裏面咧，按照個case咧喺departmental inter誒interpretation notes嗰面啦，DIPN裏面咧，來將佢細化咯。
即係依個係我依面嘅意見。
仲有冇邊一位想誒表達意見？
李慧瓊議員。
誒，我多謝大家嘅意見啦。我諗呢部分，我哋喺再逐條審議嘅陣都會去跟進。不過另一樣亦都想請教大家，因為今日都有好多業界嘅人士，我自己。
當然誒，非常之希望可以推動伊斯蘭金融喺香港嘅發展啦。但係誒，從資料上或者從我個人嘅觀察咧，就係其實香港我哋冇相應嘅文化啦。誒，比起其他一隻已經發展得好蓬勃嘅地方咧，可能我哋相關嘅條件並不是完全具備嘅。噉，我想誒，聽聽業界。
係喺呢方面嘅睇法，即係頭先大家都好正面。咁除咗呢個法例之外，其實政府有啲咩需要再做，去令到伊斯蘭金融嘅發展可以進一步係喺香港擴大咧？
邊一位可以誒講講歐生？
誒或者我答答議員呢個問題啊，因為誒誒我頭先講話依個誒草案咧個誒timing係好好時間好好啊，因為啊即係人民幣國際化咧，令到好多外國嘅投資者咧啊對人民幣好有興趣，噉啊金管局咧誒年初説亦都去過中東啦，啊推銷過人民幣啦。
咁跟住之後，個反應都好好啊！我啊，哋公司自己咧都啊接啊，有啊不同嘅啊，中東嘅啊機構咧係邀請我哋過去咧，去同佢哋去講解咩叫做人民幣國際化，同埋投資嘅機會喺邊度。噉啊，因為而家香港係啊冇可能出到super啦，噉啊，其實。
嗰個需求唔單止係美金嘅啊，人民幣嗰方嘅需求咧係會越嚟越大。咁所以我哋覺得啊，頭先啊，我亦都講嘅就係個發展個空間咧，我覺得自己可能喺人民幣啊啊super嗰方面咧個發展個空間就更加大添啊。咁所以頭先答咗完咁多，以前咧可能香港係想做呢個啊。
三億finance咧係啊個條件可能未必完全誒充足嘅，咁但係我覺得再誒向前望咧，啊我哋個機會係好大，因為誒如果還顧誒可以做到一個現時嚟講啦，一個人民幣嘅誒。
債券市場嘅中心咧，啊，香港暫時都仲係有優勢嘅。
好啊，有冇邊位啊？阿高生係噉，我簡單再補充一下啦嚇。頭先提到咁咧，就誒。
我哋誒，我覺得二零零八零九年咧，就馬來西亞政府咧曾經嚟香港咧就推廣過一次嘅，但係咧就好多人過咗去之後咧，就好似個感覺咧係有少少誒，Islamic finance係無疾而終嘅。咁點解咧？就因為好多個平台未出嚟。噉我今次咧呢個誒stamp duty
Innerverefiners咧就基本上咧就係大大咧減低咗個交易成本個transaction cost。咁點解咧？因為你誒有個Islamic finance上面有個transfer ownership啊。咁因為依個嚟講咧就in substance咧係要交多一啲税嘅。噉我哋呢度咧就立one咧作為馬來西亞咧係第二金融中心。
誒上面係納邦FinancialServiceAuthority啦，誒再上面係財政部嘅。咁咧，我哋下面咧就有個交易所，誒納邦InternationalFinancialExchange。咁馬來西亞咧就佔全世界嗰個儲庫咧個發行量咧係七成嘅喺今年嚇。咁咧就我哋依面咧又有好多人才，噉我相信咧係。
係有依個基礎咧，可以同香港政府包括呢方面咧，係直接嘅合作。
噉我提到咧就誒第二樣嘢咧，我哋嗰面咧就係誒，亦係有人民幣嘅債券嘅發行。
嚇有一間咧叫登嘉Capital咧，有五億人民幣嘅發行。噉啊，西亞政府咧亦積極咧係做一個人民幣嘅settlement。咁另外咧，亦除咗一個alternative咧，亦通過啊歐山嗰邊嘅中國銀行咧喺吉隆坡嘅辦事處咧嚟做settlement，即係話咧我哋係可以經過Benagara嚟做人民幣settlement，同埋中國銀行香港嚟做set誒set。
好嘛。
咁另外咧，有一樣我提翻咧，就係話有一有一個案例就喺喺香港聯合交易所嘅個stock曲係四三二零噉，係馬來西亞一個手提電話公司嚟嘅。噉佢嗰個bonds咧係labone嚟listing嘅，而同一時間係dual listing咧係香港嘅。我相信咧，大家頭頭先提到一大。
因為未實現過啦嚇，冇案例咧，咁可以參考呢個四三二零咧。誒，呢個馬來西亞公司而喺香港咧係掛緊嘅招牌，掛緊嘅咁可以咧係嘗試摸到或者係發現到一啲現有或者係已經操作到可以學習到嘅問題嘅。咁最後咧，我有誒誒幾幾個。
個新聞啦，可以或者喺news誒status咧，同大家可以分析下誒講講嘅。嗱，One咧除咗係國際金融中心之外咧，嗰度咧係第二我哋主要貿易咧就係國際石油貿易嘅。而頭先亦提到咧，有好多咧，因為馬來西亞嘅商人咧誒比較早咧喺誒中東嗰邊嚟做石油貿易，我哋嗰
度咧亦係有好多係中東嘅石油商咧係嚟註冊咗係做緊貿易嘅，咁所以咧呢度咧會有好多iMoney，咁可以畀到香港政府咧係一個啟發，呢個第一樣嘢。
咁第二樣嘢咧，而家咧就係馬來西亞咧，除咗咧一直咧係嗰個U.S.嘅settlement之外咧，而家係積極咧嚟做嗰個人民幣嘅settlement。咁咧就誒，仲有兩點啦嚇。第一喺五月十八號二零一二年咧，咁咧就Benaragala嗰面咧已經喺北京嘅sorry喺北京嘅馬來西亞大使館。
本個網站公佈咧，就係有十一間銀行，而家已經有十七間銀行咧嘅馬來西亞咧，係已經可以用一個system叫MyClear咧進行嗰個人民幣結算。
而同一時間咧，喺二零一一年嘅十一月咧，就中國政府嘅商務部咁咧，裏面咧已經係可以咧就係經誒提到咧就係話咧，如果你係誒有一個overseas嘅remun比嘅equivalent咧，你可以嚟作為一個現金投入入誒入去誒中國投資。
啲啊，provider咧，你商務部係誒認可嘅，咁所以咧就係話呢啲咧，好似係貶新幫或者係offshore bonds咧，係將來咧係直接咧可以幫到誒所有商人，包括政府，同埋推動咧呢個人民幣嘅國際化嘅。所以我想希望大家咧，在座咧可以誒認真考慮呢樣。
有對香港政府吸納嗰個中東嘅資金，同埋咧馬來西亞，因為好近香港，可以好容易咧係交流，同埋create到一個tax substance。咁變咗咧，希望咧喺税務嗰面咧誒，可以同埋所有嘢咧，可以雙方咧係多啲嘅誒交流。咁誒。
誒聽日咧誒，亦係香港金管局咧同Manbana Gara咧喺香港會有個會議嘅嚇。咁主要係噉樣，唔該。好啊，好啊，多謝你啊，郭生。噉啊，馬來西亞喺呢一方面嘅誒工作咧，做得相當好嘅嚇。阿梁繼昌議員，誒多謝主席。
主席，我有幾多數問題。第一個問題是 factual 問題，但係在問之前，我覺得我歡迎政府提出這個法案，我亦都支持這個法案。不過，我會提一點意見，就是可能。
Although I noted that Ms. Lina Yan said that the government has taken some time to do the consultation for the past couple of years, I do think that the the bill is a little bit late. But late is better than never. First question is just a factual question. Maybe all the guests here could could give me some information on that. I would like to know.
The Muslim population in Hong Kong and also the Muslim population in mainland China. Is there any? Maybe the government can also give me a decent piece of information about. Is there any statistics on the Muslim population in in these two jurisdictions?
啊，工傷。
嗯。
post on個after okay，yeah。
要，啊，誒，是。
見到。
about the Hong Kong Muslim population, it is estimated.
兩百萬。
and about the mainland, I don't have information, but indeed there are more than that population living in China.
and also the the area close to Hong Kong, Guangdong, Shenzhen, there are many Muslims businessmen who are settled here in in the China. They come for the business, and there are many companies of Middle East now they have opened their offices here in Hong Kong, and they want to.
start the business in Hong Kong by Islamic finance. So the local permanent resident, there are about two hundred thousand living in Hong Kong.
That is my estimate. Maybe it is different from the official statistics. Okay, thank you. Kosan, yeah, 沒有異議。Okay, I I got this figure from two sources.
第一個，我我讀個報告，五五年前，佢 mention 係穆斯林人口喺中國係約二十二萬。
And secondly, I met寧夏政府，with our deputy general directors director in Beijing，and
他 mention that no no official figure on hand probably less than thirty three or thirty thousand million, and as far as I know, besides Xinjiang or Muslim,
There's six million Chinese, six million people in寧夏and阿曼，that one third that means around two million Chinese Muslim there in寧夏autonomy area，and in河南province。
誒，just in鄭鄭州，the capital of河南。
There one million Chinese Muslims.
yeah。
Okay. Thank you.啊。
誒。
note that in in Malaysia when Islamic finance started at one point, the non-Muslims were investing more in Islamic finance than the Muslims were because of the
啊啊係歐山歐山。嗯，Yeah，嗯，I just like to say that the main market is not just Hong Kong and China. I think it's the whole of Middle East.
just to give you an example, you know there been a lot of demand for QD. Just a couple of sovereign wealth funds in the Middle East recently got a billion dollar quota, and just one institution.
and so it's not just a number of population, it's really the quantity of money that is really the driver.
阿迪哥，阿迪阿迪。
at the time, I met.
我 met the寧夏政府，他們係 Chinese Muslim in Beijing， and also the met the寧夏政府， they mentioned that it's good to raise the wholesale Islamic bonds through Hong Kong， and that's why I suggest the Hong Kong government to do more communication roadshows to the寧夏 people in
北京，and also in銀川。
And for the retail one, in 18 of May 2012, the first bank of寧夏政府，徐嘴山銀行啊，徐嘴山Bank had cooperate with a bank a bank in Malaysia, a retail bank in Malaysia, and approve about
南百納嘎拉，that's why I think that I taught you the first and second Islamic bank in寧夏，and they still planning for that。that's why I suggest the Hong Kong government to do more things to them。and the head of these two bank，the government officer of寧夏autonomy
地區， at the same time.
係啊。
I think it's also important to note that it's not just Muslim individuals, but as the number of Islamic banks and takaful companies increase, then there is a greater demand for them to be Sharia compliant, and therefore they are looking for products which are Sharia compliant, and therefore it's a snowballing effect in the sense that the greater number of
Institutions and those institutions looking for investments and of course bonds. So I think that's an important part to look at. Hong Kong would be ideally suited because it's an international centre and institutions around the world. As the numbers increase, there will be greater demand, and Hong Kong would then be able to service those. And therefore, it's not directly related.
To individual Muslims alone. Okay, Mr. Ahmed. Thank you. Just a couple of points to add on what has already been said. When it comes to institutional demand for Islamic finance, I think it's important to realise that any institution that intends to tap the Islamic finance market either by virtue of
sukuk or other structures can attract Islamic liquidity from anywhere in the world, as long as the underlying structure and documentation meets the requirements of the principles of Islamic finance. So, the actual liquidity pool that can be accessed.
是 not.
dependent just on the domestic liquidity coming from retail investors from Hong Kong or from mainland China, it would in fact be primarily directed towards attracting liquidity in the Middle East as well as in the Islamic centres of Asia. Then when it comes to the retail market.
the consumer market, of course, for those for that particular segment, having Islamic deposit and asset products would give the individual consumers the the choice and the ability to invest in line with their own sort of beliefs and their own faith. So for the for the wider
I think proposition. What we really hoping is that this initiative will enable Hong Kong-based
corporates as well as Hong Kong listed transactions to attract the vast pool of liquidity from from investors who only invest in a Sharia compliant manner. And in all the transactions, the sukuk transactions that have been done across the world, we've seen that it has proven to be the most inclusive way to tap the market.
because not only can you attract the Islamic investors, but even the conventional non-Islamic investors are you know are you know welcome to invest in the same transaction.
問Q，阿何小姐。
In fact, in answer to Miss Lee's question, there are a few things the administration can do to promote Islamic finance.
The administration should have an overall strategy to promote a broadly comprehensive Islamic finance product, such as a takafu.
Trade, finance and wealth management, in order to give more choices to investors and enhance Hong Kong's wealth status as the financial centre.
secondly， the administration should promote this， because Islamic finance is not religion bound. 65% of the consumer are non-Muslim.
所以我諗，The Ministry can also promote this concept to the investors.
In order to make this a success, I think.
We need to really train, look into the education side and training side, so that we have enough talent to support our initiative.
This is our view. Okay, thank you.啊，張生。
just to just to add to the the discussions, if we look at the interest in Islamic finance throughout the world, that's been increasing right across not just in Muslim countries. So if we look at the interest in Europe, for example, led by London, and we've also seen the French also look at it, and in Asia.
Pacific, for example, we've also seen the Japanese, the Koreans, as well as in Australia, efforts have been made to actually introduce changes in legislation to effectively provide users of finance the ability to tap also into the liquidity that the Islamic markets do.
所以從那個視角，我認為，它是相當緊迫的，就喺呢個發展上，香港政府其實睇得比較仔細，嚟到推動呢個法案，加入全球社會。
Just two follow-up questions, both on the market itself. Could our speakers today just walk me through in further detail? Because I understand that there are quite a number of sovereign wealth funds who would like to make investment in this part of the world.
Hong Kong and/or mainland China, particularly in real estate sector. Can someone enlighten me as to how the development of the Suku market in Hong Kong can help or facilitate these sovereign wealth funds or financial institutions to make
investment into Hong Kong or China? That's my first question.
The second question relates to a comment made by Mr. Asher just a few minutes ago. He mentioned about Islamic mortgage. I just want to address this question to the Hong Kong government.
Are there any regulatory or taxation hurdle which would prohibit the introduction of Islamic mortgage product in Hong Kong? Yeah, these are my two questions. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Okay, thank you.
有邊位啊，Mr.阿麥？
In relation to your first question, I think Islamic finance can be instrumental in two ways in attracting sovereign wealth funds to invest in, particularly in the real estate sector in Asia and in this in in Hong Kong and mainland China. Firstly,
A lot of investors prefer for the underlying stock or the shares of the companies that they're investing to be Sharia compliant, and there's a certain set of rules that have been accepted and by
international index managers, for example, the Dow Jones Islamic Index, wherein no more than say one third of the debt that is taken by a particular company can be non-Islamic or interest-bearing debt, for it to for the underlying stock to qualify as being.
Sharia compliant. Therefore, for maintaining Sharia compliance of the equity, it's important to be able to leverage a particular investment on an Islamic basis, and that's where the significance of Islamic debt and instruments like sukuk comes in.
and then of course in addition to that particular benefit, which would create more liquidity in the underlying stocks because there's a greater investor following, the the other advantage is that by structuring the debt on a if I may use that term on an on a Sharia compliant basis.
We are able to tap the widest possible investor base, as I mentioned earlier. So the ability of those transactions to be executed successfully at the best possible pricing is enhanced by having those underlying.
transactions structured to be Sharia compliant.
Thank you.
Mr. Nasser, as I said, the I like the way in which this ordinance has been drafted in sense that it it
It gives you the essential features, but leaving everything else flexible. And therefore, I think it would be easier for those who structure these within the bill to be able to do that as well as comply with the provisions of the ordinance. And so, from that perspective, I do like its flexibility.
係。
In the sense that it retains, actually, there must be quite a lot of research done.
It's amazing that not having a Sharia scholar, I'm not sure they had a Sharia scholar, but they've actually distilled the key features that are required in order to put together Islamic structure, but left all the other details out, and therefore.
it it will provide some flexibility there.
好，散。
yes.
Just want to go back to the theme of RMB internationalisation. Just answering the question whether the Suku development would be useful for investment. In fact, it's not just a one-way traffic. As I explained earlier, that you know, with the trade between China and Middle East.
Increases over time, there will be excess RMB being accumulated in the region. And for those Middle East investors who who are for religious reason want to invest in Sharia investment product, then we need to provide them with that vehicle. But from a corporate perspective,
By raising offshore人民幣throughZKs， it will facilitate that foreign direct investment into China. As you know now, there's a policy differentiation between dollar FDI and人民幣FDI. I don't want to go into detail. We don't need to here. But and further further down the road.
你 also mentioned where the Swiss the sovereign wealth fund raising.
making investment in China, I think for several reasons. I I think ultimately the goal we would like to see is to have人民幣being treated as a reserve currency.
And for that to happen, you need to have a matured capital market to provide liquidity, and that's why the development of the sukuk is so important in my view. Thanks. Okay, Mr. Edigal.
我 try to sum up your two questions into two point. One is the compliance, the second one is costing.
For compliants啊，all school need in Malaysia，all school issued need to fulfil Sarah principle，and those with professional people from Sarah bodies。
所以，我會suggest內Revenue， to in order to speed up the the issue and so on. So I would suggest an內Revenue department to include such a professional body or professional people into your committee team or even in the DIPN.
啊啊啊！college there。
And to speed up the compliance issues, and also to the other commercial institute as well.
And secondly，呃，呃。
For your partner property, for for some of the case that would include hotel projects. I recall that hotel is not allowed to to be included in the sukuk. So if yours is only property project, that's good. But if it includes some kind of a hotel element, so
它應該被排除。
for other other exception interest, I don't want to mention here.
嗯。
The other one mortgage for sukuk interest element is not allowed inside, but probably you can repackage it as some kind of a discount issues or.
或其他 banking charges arrangement， as I mentioned before， so so I think commercial institutions need to aware of those terms and the promotion。 that's that would be quite strict。
呃，from the Sarvus principle and Islamic principles， very strict啊，and also propaganda promotion as well。
And finally, I want to do bring in bring out a business case from not Iran Iraq.
我 read from book that after the US enter into the Iraq, that would be a huge demand in Islamic finance there, and the Islamic finance arrangement in Iraq differs from province.
所以，那會帶我另一條到中國。
因為中華人民共和國中央政府。
said that Islamic finance would be in寧夏，呃，銀川啊。
所以我唔sure喺未來，Islamic arrangement in寧夏或或銀川會唔會與其他省份從中國不同。所以我想，我會建議IRD aware of this point and try to create flexibility as far as possible, but at the same time.
I think that will be, I foresee that there will be a conflict or maybe difficulties in terms of jurisdiction and test substance. Yeah, that's why. Mr. Ashton.
其實，實際上，這些兩個問題，是 not related to me。 Government or some expert in the institution can answer。 But for the basic， the mortgage， conventional mortgage and Islamic mortgage has a difference。 In Islamic mortgage
the individual or bank, both are the partner in in the property. Like if an individual pay twenty percent, he is the owner of only twenty percent. Against the conventional way of mortgaging, that the bank give the loan.
In this way, it is not allowed because it is interest based. So the Islamic way, he is owner of only twenty percent or ten percent, whatever he is paying. The rest is the rest owner is the bank. Then the bank give on on rent basis.
to that individual.
at the end when the bank receive his its cast or with profit then with the the last instalment he sell this the eighty percent portion of that property to the individual so in this way religiously it becomes
Okay, and individual is happy, and also the bank is safe.
誒政府有冇咩回應啊？
我諗，under the bill， of course， if property transactions are involved as part of the structure for Islamic sukuk， the bill actually seek to exempt them from stamp duty。但going back to the Islamic or mortgage issue，我諗。
I heard Mr. Ko explained it very well, terms and also also the chief in Hong Kong. So systemically, we are not sort of seeing problems brought to our attention per se, but we are open to look into it if there are any taxation.
Issues that may be involved in that respect, but if I may just take the opportunity to respond to the various call for for the promotion and contact with other authorities for promoting Islamic finance in Hong Kong, I think we do very much value the opportunity.
To go into contact and learn more from the Malaysian authorities, and I think thank you for the very good advice that we should also step up contacts with other parties, including the Ningxia and Yenchuan authorities in that respect. So, and also we will look into the sort of professional training.
situation to see whether there's can be strengthened partnership of various entities involved.
唔係。
梁議員長，誒，多謝主席，我冇再有其他問題，唔該。好，社立謙議員。
Thank you, Chairman. Chairman, I like to ask Imam.
馬夫蒂阿查特，to to enlighten us， this legislation is a is neutral as to religion。 can this type of legislation be practical that be neutral to religion and how does this compare to other Malaysian
相似立法。
所以，如果它被做為香港的法律，我認為它會對所有人好，而且它不會對任何一國有約束力去處理伊斯蘭金融，但它是給那些
who want to make business a deal at want to get the house through Islamic finance, so it is a facility I believe, and also the same time it is in the past few years and in many words in many countries of the world, it is proven that.
It is a safe transaction finance, and it is good for everyone.
actually，the Islamic finance
It's not only only for the Muslim, like it has been adopted in UK, as it has been mentioned, and some other in France and some other non-Muslim countries. So it is a facility for the resident and for other people who want to invest in Hong Kong.
and they are Muslim and they want to make a business in Islamic way, so that would be a good chance and good opportunity for them. No, my my question is, because this legislation is
中立， in terms of religion. Yes.
But my my question is actually, I just seek some understanding. How can this divorce from the shari, from the Islamic law, when you have such a a a instrument
can it be in this legislation? Do you see this it being successful, being neutral to religion? That's my question.
好，我哋問問啊啊啊，Mission阿Sir。
If I can help, as I said earlier, the prime we've got.
the specific products that the contracts that are mentioned here, what they've done in this legislation is is extract the primary.
元素 of those products.
and therefore, it's
Sharia compliant in the sense that it is broadly accepted that those are the essential characteristics of those contracts. For instance, if it's wakala, it's agency and therefore it's agency. If it's musharakah, then it's a partnership. And therefore, if you look at those specific contracts under Sharia, those
特定元素 for those contracts have been incorporated in in the ordinance, but all the other detail has been left out. And therefore, I think it's flexible enough, and therefore it's compliant with Sharia to that extent. Anyone looking at it would say, Ah, yes, the primary elements within each of those contracts are there.
Whether or not there's going to be compliance would be up to the Sharia scholar, and that he would look at the details. And the details, which I've said, hopefully would come under DIPN. But as as the primary elements concerned, there within that, and those who are
familiar with Islamic products and Islamic contracts will know that those primary elements of the contracts are already incorporated there. So, so this legislation is not in itself a isolated case. It still have to be subjected to the Sharia laws, right? No, it's.
誒。
Sharia law is doesn't apply in Hong Kong. This is the law in Hong Hong Kong, and what it's done is it's incorporated the primary elements, but it doesn't say that Sharia law shall apply. But this would the Sharia law would apply to the products, would it? In in
in essence, anybody wishing to come and to Hong Kong and and create a product.
would look at the ordinance to to seek the specific exemptions because in in having an Islamic contract, you need a number of steps because Islamic contract in a finance you just have a loan and you have interest on that, but for an Islamic contract you need to have a number of steps. For instance, trade in a product.
being sold back and forth, and that creates under our present ordinance liability to tax. And what this does is remove that liability to tax for the specific purpose of
That trade which is required to make finance possible, so Islamic finance is not actually.
finance as in banking finance, but
requiring banks to become traders in, in effect, and therefore it allows
for that particular exemption for the particular tax that would arise in Hong Kong, but and I'm quite happy that it's neutral because within Islam there's so many different schools of law that one school may disagree with another school and it's.
not really helpful to have all of that within our structure, and therefore the neutrality of it is actually quite useful to everyone.
That's that's what sorry。啊，議員啊，我聽過張張敏敏先啦，主席。我想跟my my my understanding which limited understanding。 But the Islamic laws is infiltrated into every part of one life. How can it a legislation be neutral of this Islamic law？啊，Is that is that my understanding is？
wrong。
Well, Islamic law, as far Muslims are concerned, it affects him in every aspect of his life. And Imam Marshed is the the scholar on that. But as far as others are concerned, it is no more than for those who are non-Muslims. It is no more than somebody an institution saying, well, we want to.
invest in social
socially responsible investing. So that means we don't want tobacco, we don't want alcohol, we don't want. And so somebody investing on that basis would be very close to Islamic. Somebody investing on Islamic principles, except that they've got additional elements of interest involved in it. The reason why I want to ask is this: we want to.
Go in with our eyes open rather than just we like the products and we can accept a lot of things that which we don't understand. Yeah, and that's the whole purpose of today's meeting here, you know, so that we can seek understanding from the enlightened ones. Yes.
I hope that I hope my answer have enlightened you on that, Mr. Ahmed.
Yes, I just want to elaborate that.
for any specific transaction that would incorporate the provisions of this bill, there would actually be transaction specific documentation. That documentation would benefit from providing tax neutrality effectively to Islamic finance as compared to conventional. So this
really serves to level the playing field for Islamic finance transactions to be no more expensive than conventional transactions from a taxation point of view. The governing law of any particular documentation would be the either the local law that is recognised in the jurisdiction.
或，它可為國際法，例如，它可為英法，或，的法，任何其他，國際上接受的，管轄權。
The approval process for a particular transaction document would involve going to certain internationally recognised, well-renowned Sharia scholars.
所以，他們會 look at the particular structure，他們會 look at the documentation， and notwithstanding the fact that the
governing law could be English law or Hong Kong law. They will evaluate the structure and the documentation under the principles of Islamic finance.
And if the if if they believe that the structure and documentation complies with the principles of Islamic finance, they will approve it to be Sharia compliant. But the documentation doesn't need to be governed by Sharia law for them to do that. And therefore, what we're really doing here is providing the enabling legislation for.
transactions to be structured such that they can then be you know compliant both with the relevant governing law as well as the principles of Islamic finance. Thank you. Then my next question is: Have there been any cases in other jurisdictions where such alternative bonds took place?
That there have been a non-compliance to the to the Sharia laws that eventually end up in court. That this would put the investors into a rather embarrassed or a disadvantaged position.
Yes, Mr. Leggo, you want to add? I'm not sure whether I can answer your question exactly, but I would try to bring out three cases for your reference. First of all, London, besides Malaysia, London and Dubai is another two key Islamic centres, and
According to the, I remember that according to the law in London, they still adopt the religion-neutral approach. I think from government's point of view, there's no ground to impose Islamic jurisdiction into their laws.啊。
In Malaysia as well.
And that's why I just proposed IRD to include a SAR member into their department and in the committee and DIPN.
This is the first first point. The second one, I read from their two business case. I think more than the deal structure. If the Islamic bankers or other bankers they want to deal with their investors.
或試圖安排某種類的伊斯蘭金融安排給他們的投資者，他們需要包括。
profession from several bodies to comply several principle. I think that's a
something on top of government jurisdictions。
The first case is a normalless case in La Bon，所以。
啊！
the lawmaker。
try to rearrange the deal structure from a conventional deal structure into an Islamic deal structure, to with an opinion from several bodies. So I think that you can take this as a reference for that. And second one is Esther AX.
IATA， that's related to the listing one for stock code four three two O。
They use their airtime. Their mobile carrier. They use their airtime as an undertaking.
to arrange the deal structure to issue Islamic sukuk.
So I think I cannot. This can answer part of your questions.
Thank you. So I think you you might be interested. There was a case in England, Bexco and Kuwait Finance. I think which one of the parties having taken a loan in Islamic finance then said, well, this is not.
In accordance with Islamic law, and tried to introduce that, and the court said.
It is not the application of Islamic law. It's an application of contract law. Therefore, you can't actually incorporate Islamic law into our laws just because you're incorporating some of the elements. And in fact, in Malaysia, there was a case where the judges tried to interpret.
Islamic principles within the judgement, and I think they changed the rule now that only Bank of Negara has a special interpretation unit which will interpret Islamic principles for the purpose of.
those products rather than the courts, and so even in Malaysia they've addressed that. So it's not going to be, and I've not known of any other country, not even Pakistan, unless they have a specific Islamic court where they can impose Islamic law, because it's not really certain which Islam
Islamic law would apply because actually there are five schools of thought. So I know there are countries like India, Pakistan, Singapore that do have Islamic courts in relation to certain parts, but then those are well defined and set out. So there's no problem about incorporating Islamic law into
Common law country, because even if we were we were to follow being a common law country, looking at Malaysia, they haven't got any authorities that we could adopt because Bank Negara has taken over that. Yep, my sorry, chairman, my my my limited knowledge and my my ignorance actually put me into this.
number of questions that under the common law we enter into a contract. If the contract, the the product that we enter into that
contract。
That product is subjected to Sharia laws. The Sharia law is an interpretation that could be open because there's no, as you said, there's no law. So when you enter into contract or something that is wrong, doesn't make it doesn't make the contract right. That's that's my my that was covered in Becksimco. So if you read the
The Beximco judgment and Kuwait Finance and Kuwait Bank, then that's covered in that. And as I said earlier, and the courts haven't incorporated Sharia law into contracts. And in fact, that's that's good. And I think you've you've covered some aspects of that. Mr. Ahmed.
我認為關鍵點是，這個合約的管轄法不是沙裏亞法。這個合約符合伊斯蘭金融的原則，但管轄法仍然是普通法或英國法。謝謝你的解釋。
Mr.阿Sir，Yes，actually，it is just the facility，are opening a window for those who want to make their business according to their religious requirement，so it has no contradiction with。
others or it is not.
taking out from the overall laws of the country or the finance finance law. So just it is a facility, I believe, for those who want to deal, or even the investors who want to keep their investment safe. So this is one of the way that they can deal.
透過伊斯蘭 finance。謝謝。Mr. Edigol。
One point, additional point to Mr. Nansha, or may be part of a answer to to this gentleman. So Malaysia adapt the common law, and so pusher Malaysia, and they adapt they are onshore. But we Labuan, we have we are offshore, and we adapt the common law as well.
But we have additional Islamic legislation on top of Malaysia, so I think that I agree with that. This gentleman that both would not be contradicted, so because.
the the one who arrange a deal would look at both law at the same time.
O.K.李慧瓊議員，你係咪有問題？冇問題啦，係嘛？梁繼昌議員。
多謝主席。I just want to follow up these these legal issues. Now, although I understand that in interpreting the the transaction documentation, it is the governing law is either sometimes English law or New York law which will be relevant for the instrument.
But I hope, I mean, the the influence of the Islamic law is still there. I hope I can answer honourable Abraham Schack's question. For example, if you got a suit court, I think the issue would invariably appoint a Sharia committee, and and that is a specified committee with scholars sitting.
There, and I do think invariably, I think in these transaction documents, either as a termination event or event of default, if if the Sharia committee rules that the the product is no more Sharia compliant, is my understanding correct?
入邊咪可以。Yes, so I mean, if if the products are usually structured on the basis that they receive approval being Sharia compliant, but there is within some products there's flexibility as well from the sharia. As we said, you've heard the five percent, the one third rule, five percent rule. They apply in different levels and also different.
學校，所以， yes。
張生，Mr.張。Just to add from the various discussions, and again, when you look at the governing law of the contracts, and also for the the sukuk, for example, it's either if it's international, it's English law, New York law, Malaysian law, Singapore law, for example.
the getting the Sharia opinion is one aspect of it.
and that's a deliverable for the bond offering itself and the Sharia opinion itself is relevant for investors who require them and this will be investors who are Islamic investors. so it doesn't preclude conventional investors from investing in this sukuk as well. so from that
perspective， you know， non-share compliance at the end of the day is not an event of default， because the bonds was the securit themselves was carry on as an instrument for the five years or the ten years that they are issued for。
所以，the delivery of the Sharia opinion is just one aspect of that. And to gain the broadest base of investors, the arrangers of these bond offerings will use a panel of internationally recognised Sharia scholars to provide their pronouncement, so that the investor base can actually.
as as broad investor base can actually buy into these products.
Mr.誒咩？
Usually in a
depending on the kind of product, there would be provisions built into the contract that are meant to ensure ongoing Sharia compliance. So, for example, if a contract is structured against a pool of real estate assets, if there is a need to dispose of those assets for some reason during the life of the sukuk, there would be a provision in the contract that provides
Provides for the replacement of those assets with other Shariah compliant assets, so that underlying lease arrangements can essentially continue. So you know that that should ensure that Shariah compliance is not at risk on an ongoing basis, as long as the conditions of the document are.
secondly, I think it's important to realise that Islamic finance has been evolving over the last couple of decades and will continue to evolve. And new instruments, new types of underlying assets have come into the fold.
There are, however, no precedents of a previously approved.
Islamic transaction being declared to be non-compliant by the scholars with retrospective effect.
所以，even though new forms of Islamic contracts have or application of Islamic contracts have been introduced, for example, the first sukuk was only done on the basis of a sale and leaseback structure, but now there have been several other types of structures done. That doesn't mean that what's been done in the past has been effectively.
You know, renounced in any way by the scholars. There are no precedents of that having happened.
哦，陳明欣。
主席，我 just want have one one follow up question. Although I think Mr. Cheung has rightly point out that the non compliance, I mean, I mean the compliance process is a continuous process, right? Although Mr. Cheung has point out that the the the non compliance, for example, during the term of the instrument is not a
一，個事件 of default，但commercially speaking or practically speaking，what implications it will have if during the term of the to the investors of course I'm talking about the protection of investors，what what legal implication or practical implication would it have if
The instrument during the middle of the term is not Sharia compliant. What will happen, in fact?
是真呢？ sir。
In in part of the amendments that I suggested, I had put in certain aspects where there would be replacement of the product. So, whereas where you get a a situation of that situation of that nature.
It's within the experience of those formulating it to be able to change product, replace product. So it's not unusual if if it's but usually these things are considered well in advance anyway. But if if an event should arise, then you can replace product.
And we, I've suggested that within the amendments.
好，張生。
Yeah, sorry, just just to reiterate it.
When I talk about non-compliance, effectively, as as as mentioned as explained within the documentation itself, right, it does provide for you know the assets to be able to be replaced. So if for whatever reasons the assets become non-compliant, right, the issuer has a right to be able to replace those assets and then.
It's an undertaking that they have to replace those assets. So to date, we haven't seen any non-compliance from that perspective. That's why you don't build into the sukuk structure itself an event of default from that perspective, just because it's a Sharia non-compliant, because it's it's provided for in the contract itself.
冇其他問題啦嘛。
就誒。
啊，Sirajmi，我like to follow up with the question. That the the right of replacement is on the not.
to the extent that this could disadvantage the investors, is there any protection for the investors when there have been a change of products because of non-compliance?
Talking on protection of the investors.
邊一位可以答，Mr.鍾？Yeah, it will be the same type of product. So if it's a sale and leaseback, for example, generally it will be a sale and leaseback as well. When there is a value, when there is value change, value can go up and value can go down. Yeah, but it it has to be of the same value. Then it went down. This means that there has been effect on the
on the on the contract.
I mean, have I make myself clear? Just to complete, it's the replacement of the same value. Okay. Right, so you you're not replacing something which is more inferior. Thank you.
Mr. Ahmed，Ahmed。
I think it's important to make the distinction that.
investor protection in the context of ongoing Sharia compliance is different from the value of the investment. So I think this is exactly the kind of risk that we have to be mindful of. That sometimes if investors are losing money on an investment, they may want to consider you know whether the is
any way to sort of seek recourse on the grounds that an investment has become non-sharia compliant, you know, so as far as Sharia compliance is concerned, you know, as long as the asset is replaced with a comparable asset in case
there is destruction of the asset or that asset needs to be taken out of the pool for some reason, you know, then Shariah compliance on an ongoing basis is ensured. Now what we
ensure in these sukuk bonds is that every investor has the opportunity to look at the certification of the structure that has been provided by the Sharia scholars, and based on that, the investors make the determination of whether they are comfortable with the disclosure.
of the nature of the underlying contract as being Sharia compliant from their perspective. So by investing in that transaction, they are acknowledging that they understand the structure and they they they accept the the fact that it is considered to be Sharia compliant from their perspective. So to the extent nothing changes in
fundamental structure.
If they change their view, that doesn't necessarily, you know, mean that the underlying structure has become non-compliant at a later stage. Thank you for for this detailed explanation. You see, the the reason why we have to ask so many questions because
We are legislating in uncharted waters.
A lot of things that this is something new to us. I mean, as to me, I think it's something that is very important that we know exactly what we are legislating for. Not that we don't trust government. That we we are here to check on the government and we just want to know how much they understand this, so that as legislators we have to ask for.
This question, possibly, we haven't asked enough because we don't know what to ask. As I said, that these are all uncharted waters, and it's very important that we must need to know. Thank you. Absolutely.
啊。
啊，歐生，歐生。嗯，嗯，I just want to add that we shouldn't penalise Sharia financial products for being non-Sharia running the risk of non-Sharia compliance. Because actually deep down we're talking about governance issue, and conventional financial instruments have the same issue. So I think just want to bring that point up.
但係，係稍為不同，因為。
你係講緊啲普通財務問題或者產品，whatever it is，但係佢哋唔受某啲宗教法規影響。所有啲宗教法規係同其他產品唔同，係商業性質，係商業原則，係商業理解。宗教法規係超越。
human understanding of the ordinary people, because it's based on a number of Sharia scholars. The scholars itself has explained to us there are five different schools, and that five different schools could come into different interpretation. Like even in Hong Kong with the Basic Law, when we have when we have problems.
去go to NPC，the National People's Congress，to seek interpretation， but our interpretation rests on the vast scholars. That scholars their thinking and the religious belief is different. So that's why we have to be so careful. It's other a lot of other people's money putting into an investment. Not that we don't trust this particular.
We need to understand more. That's all.
嗯。
會，咪少咗？Yes, actually there are five different school of thought. But in finance there is only one school of thought. They are all five agreed, and you can see the same finance in Iran, same in Dubai, same. Actually.
we there are different school of thought that is not related to finance. There are other issues, other practical, other ibada like worshiping, like punishment, some others. But in the finance, there is consign, consensus, and there is.
agree, agreement among all the scholars. So I believe there will be no problem in this field.
我嗱，我哋誒。
現場嗰個會議嘅時間咧，係去到。
十點四十五分啦，好嘛？因為大家都好踴躍去。
去到泳中。
係咯，係咯，係咯，啊，誒。
Mr. Nasher, you want to respond? I think it's it might be easy to understand in the sense that as far as Islamic finance is concerned, it's basically the Islamic rule is everything is determined by contracts and agreement between the parties, so it's primarily a question of contract. The only thing the only thing where
Islamic law applies is in the prohibition, what you are not allowed to do, which is basically, as Imam Marzooq said, uncertainty, gambling, interest. So one really looks at what is not allowed from the Islamic principle, rather than Islamic law as such. It's only what is not allowed, and that's those few elements.
Okay, Mr. Edigal.
我 just want to mention that, but mentioned already. I think the key is the deal structure, and the key is the lawyer and the the banker, and that's why we adopt a religious neutral approach.
for fear that the religious law will supersede the common the common law or contract law.
And the other point, I want to remind the IRD is in my in the consultation my opinion to the consultation paper.
I remember that there would be at least 11 11 kinds of different kinds of sukuk in Malaysia, and then four four popular ones. So if I would recommend you include these four cases.
或誒， in your SAR members or誒 opinions in your DIPN。
Because these four are most popular one. Okay, thank you.
其他議員仲有冇咩跟進？冇啦，唔講啦嚇。O K，好啊，阿梁議員。誒，just one more follow up question。Um, in case there are new, 啊，suku products to be included, I just want to clarify. Um, it would be included as a subsidiary legislation, or could it be included
在DIPN itself， maybe the government can answer this question。
呃，楊小姐，question is to include it as a piece of subsidiary legislation that the financial secretary can move for negative vetting by the legislative council. So I I guess that the DIPs can also supplement or the other amendments.
administrative details with regard to interpretation and so on. But then, if an expansion of the coverage is required, we usually we propose to do it through the making of a piece of subsidiary legislation.
冇其他嘢嚇，冇其他嘢啦。噉我亦喺度咧，係再一次多謝咁多位團體嘅代表出席今次嘅會議嚇。誒，你係提供咗好好嘅誒意見嚇，不管係喺市場裏邊嘅誒專業嘅睇法，或者係喺我哋草擬呢一個法例嗰方面咧，都提咗好有誒。
嗯誒有用嘅有建設性嘅意見嚇，咁喺處咧多謝你哋嘅出席，好嘛？多謝曬，今日你哋就誒，因為跟住落去我哋仲有處理其他嘅事務，好嘛？多謝你哋出席嚇。
啊！各位同事，就我哋上一次誒討論嘅文件裏邊咧，仲有一份咧係要誒跟進嚇嘅嚇。噉就係文件咧，C B一六九三一二一三，佢回一三號嘅文件。咁或者誒誒副秘書長，你做一個簡單嘅介紹好嘛？
誒好啊！多謝主席。我諗誒，剛才嗰個同誒業界啊，同埋議會人士嘅討論都可能有啲牽涉誒誒頭誒，我哋文件嗰個誒嗰個一啲範疇啦。咁主要誒誒喺上一次個誒法案草案委員會咧，就問到關於誒我哋誒喺。
你收集即係嗰個公眾諮詢意見嗰個結果，同埋咧就係話，即係啲誒其他司法管轄區喺呢方面嘅發展嘅做法，同埋好似頭先其實誒個討論都有大部分涉及咧，就係話誒伊斯蘭債券喺內地金融市場嘅投資環境，或者係啲誒嗰啲。
啲誒人民幣啊，或者係嗰個主權基金方面，或者我我睇睇誒，其實誒第三點喺頭先都有誒相當嘅討論，或者我只係補充於關於咧誒我哋喺嗰個公眾諮詢收集翻嚟嗰個意見嗰個結果方面嘅問題。當然頭先都有誒與會者。
就提出咗，包括嗰個涵蓋嘅範圍啊，誒方面，噉我哋都係有積極回應啦，加翻咗個代理安排啦，同埋喺誒嗰個草案裡面咧，就係誒有啲彈性，在日後有個機制去增加呢個誒其他嘅種類嘅。噉就誒最緊要咧，就係有一啲。
喺誒喺符合嗰個誒喺誒嗰個税務方面咧，誒因為個伊斯蘭債券嘅產品嘅結構係比較獨特啦。但係而家我哋希望佢能夠喺各種税務方面有啲豁免，變咗喺嗰個誒彈性誒便利市場發展同埋一個即係税務嗰個執行上面咧，係都係要攞。
啲平衡嘅咁當中，我哋譬如喺嗰個最長年期咧，誒誒，最初我哋嗰個建議咧，就係話嗰個伊斯靈伊斯蘭債券咧最長個，如果產品可以到十年噉，但係我哋都收集咗一啲市場嘅意見啦，我覺得誒可以仲可以誒畀多啲彈性嘅。
處理噉，我哋呢度亦都係相對調整咗咧，就係而家係誒法例之下咧，就話可以唔超過十五年嘅誒。如果佢係要係即係話受惠於呢啲噉嘅税務個誒寬免，噉就譬如誒另外就係話，譬如記錄嗰啲誒被存嗰個時間咧，以往亦都係比。
比較係嚴緊啊，超過十年噉樣啊。而家咧係我哋修訂係一個比較啊啊相相對寬鬆嘅做法，就係話喺嗰個事件發生七年，或者係啊嗰個成個嗰個啊產品咧，嗰個誒年期完咗之後三年噉樣樣，咁都係有一個寬鬆嘅處理。其他。
有一啲我哋原底要求嘅咧，我哋都係刪除咗嘅。咁誒，當然咧，最對於即係所謂嗰個誒合理嗰個投資回報咧，咁呢個咧其實亦係都係取取一個平衡，因為鑑於呢個產品嗰個獨特嘅性質，佢係一個債券嘅，但係亦都有。
其他嘅債券種類，譬如啊股股本嘅債券嘅安排。噉，但係我哋亦都係吸納咗市場嘅意見，就希望喺嗰個誒誒草案法例下邊定立大原則之餘咧，喺嗰個税務局長嗰個執行指引嗰度咧，係會更加有多啲清晰嗰個誒一啲係。
誒所謂指引畀誒市場人士去參考嘅咁呢度，我我相信可以仲有空間係誒。税務局長同市場人士係有啲討論噉，但係我哋覺得誒係用執行指引個方式嗰個表表述咧係比較係誒實際上嘅執行係仲便捷啲嘅，對於市場人士嚟講。
咁所以，我諗誒總體個回應，我諗係就住呢幾點嚇。
好，多謝主席。
同事有冇咩問題啊？
嗱，如果冇問題嘅話咧，就誒。
我哋處理咗呢一份文件，噉就我哋下一次嘅會議咧，我哋先至去做呢個逐條嘅審議嘅工作。噉我要提一提大家嘅咧，就係誒，我哋就預。
預備咗幾個時間咧，係作為我哋下一次審議嘅誒會議嘅時間嘅，噉就係二零一三年四月五號，請大家記低好嘛。
誒，四月五號就星期五。
下晝兩點半。
四月十五號星期一。
下晝四點半。
同埋咧，係四月三十號嘅上晝十點半，誒十點九。
好嘛？嗱，我我會誒誒再進一步問問咧，就係即係其他啲同事，因為今日誒有好多同事都冇出席。四月五號咧，有可能誒有啲同事係未必喺香港，但係我會問問咗先，好嘛？噉啊初步定咧就四月五號誒下晝兩點半啊，但係我會誒再問問。
問其他同事咧，因為如果到時候，因為我哋要有個column嘅，啊，今日誒而家我哋得三個同事喺度，啊，噉我就會再問一問啊，阿梁繼昌嘅。啊，主席啊，你你諗住係每一個誒？
疫情嗰度係大概幾耐啊？嗰三個啊會議，你講緊有，難都係兩個鐘頭啊！兩個鐘頭，一次都係兩個鐘頭嘅。O K，得，好嘛？O K。
噉就誒，我哋會誒確定咗個時間咧，會盡快通知嚇政府方面啦。好冇？噉啊，我宣佈今日嘅會議咧，到此結束。多謝各位。